[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software hello everyone welcome to this
episode of software engineering radio
Our Guest today is AB Fara abai is an
engineering leader with over 15 years of
experience leading product Dev teams and
building scalable systems abai has built
up his expertise in Cloud architecture
and data integration with a focus on
reliability and devops in this episode
we are talking with aai on his
experience building a cloud foundation
for oil and gas production operations
it's so good to have you on today AB
welcome to the show is there anything
you'd like to add to your bio before we
get started thank you Gan for nice
introduction I guess you covered
everything but I would like to start
this talk with a brief introduction
about oil and gas industry so oil and
gas industry covers basically two kind
of companies one is the oil and gas
company and second one is the companies
which are providing services to IR guest
company so I'm from the domain where we
provide services and I from the Upstream
Services Company where we provide all
kind of services in including hardware
and drilling the oil wells and software
whatever needed to explore and extract
the hydrocarbons from beneath the Earth
can we start with the business goal on
the move to the cloud what outcome was
the business looking for sure so I'm
from Upstream production domain so in
any Upstream company there could be
different segment it could be drilling
or wi line or production Assurance I am
from production assurance and our goal
was to use the existing infrastructure
whatever available and expand over that
infrastructure to build and deliver the
Innovative solution to the client so
what that means existing infrastructure
means before moving to the cloud we were
using some production data management
software those are mostly on Prime based
desktop application and we were storing
the data in some SQL server or Oracle
and basically developing some reports on
those desktop app but these apps were
limited in terms of scalability because
we were not able to run workflows like
where we need a lot of historical data
involved to run some machine learning
workflows so we decided to move this
data to the cloud so that we can run
Advanced workflow where we can
see the historical records maybe more
than 25 years of date of any well and we
can develop new apps like give the
recommendation about any well in real
time or do the well surveillance or do
the forecasting and there are some other
things like doing the digital twins
operation for any hardware or equipment
installed in the field so to achieve
this kind of advanced workflow the first
need was to have this data already and
collect it on any Cloud platform so that
we can expand it using machine learning
workflows or some recommendation engine
what what was our main business goal
sorry what is digital twins operation so
digital twins is an important concept
for any upstream or Midstream operation
where we basically model any physical
process or physical equipment so
whenever there is some equipment
installed in the field where oil is
producing or there is any production
facility so we can create a model of
that physical equipment in Cloud so
whenever we are ingesting data in the
cloud and we want to represent the
physical equipment as a digital entity
so that we can understand what is the
equipment behavior when some incident
happen so digital twin basically helped
us to model this kind of equipment
behavior in digital world can you give
us an idea of the size of the data that
we're talking about here in a typical
small oil and gas company maybe that
compan is owning let's say 500 Wells and
any oil well can have the oil flowing
maybe last 20 years or maybe there are
some Welles who are flowing or producing
the oil maybe last 100 year as well so
the data volume depends on the life of
the oil well and the number of oil wells
owned by any oil and good gas company so
for example let's say if there is major
national Oil Company who has more than
10,000 Wells and because National oil
companies they are producing oil since
long so they may have data for more than
50 years and second aspect of this
volume is related to the frequency so in
any oil field the frequency of data
depends on the kind of operation we are
performing it could be a second based
frequency data as well and it could be
weekly daily monthly half early or
yearly these different aspect defines
the volume of the data but the bare
minimum could be a second based
frequency data coming for more than 100
properties from any oil well and a
simple multiplication will give you a
million or billion of data point is
streaming from any field for second
based frequency data with a million or
billion of data points I do expect that
it's really critical to have your Cloud
deployment close to where the sensors
are what was your strategy in picking
Cloud regions that you're deploying to
yeah whenever we are doing any
commercial agreement with any client
these clients are mostly oil and gas
companies whenever they discuss the
requirement they always come up with the
data residency aspect so for example
let's say some client in Middle East and
Asia they are not very much comfortable
in sending their data outside Middle
East but there are some clients like in
South America they are still okay to
have their data in USA based on the
client requirement we just set a clear
expectation for example let's say we
always want uh to have the cloud project
or the cloud cluster closer to the
actual data source because it help us to
ingest data as fast as we can but if
there is some limitation from client
side and if they are okay to with the
ination latency then we basically we
still try like which regon is close to
that particular cine but the first
requirement is to understand the data
residency aspect because that is more
important but for one of the client like
in South America and that client was
okay to have their Cloud project in USA
for that we are able to ingest the data
with some latency Gap I mean it was
minimal it was not very much huge
consideration for the injection aspect
but yeah mostly for second best data or
even for the higher frequency data we
always set a clear expectation to client
and based on that we decide our
injection time Laten and consumption
time latency what were the metrics you
were using to track success as the
project kicked off as I said our old
application was mostly on Prim and our
main challenge was we were only
delivering feature maybe once in a year
and we were spending a lot of money on
the hardware cost where it is mostly
around deploying these desktop based
application to the client field major
success criteria was if we want to spend
money on this Cloud infrastructure so
the first thing in our mind was how can
we deliver features
incrementally and as soon as possible as
we built it instead of relying on is
slow software delivery cycle and second
thing was how can we customize this
application easily per client the old
application was mostly we were were
giving a fixed kind of workflow to all
clients but here what we want to do I
mean we should be able to customize the
workflow as per the client need let's
say if some client is interested in
seeing certain dashboard in certain way
so we have those flexibility in place so
the major success criteria was to
deliver feature with agility and be able
to work as for the client need and
customize these workflow
put yourself back you know whenever you
got started with this project how was
the approach to getting the project
kicked off were you evaluating Cloud
providers were you forming a new team
were you worrying about how you will
train them was there a plan to create an
awareness and a mind Shi about devops
and other operational criteria to the
team just give us a overview of what was
discussions we started our Cloud Journey
Back in the year 2016 it's almost 8
years ago now that time our main goal
was to develop something quick and
showcase some demo to our client our
main goal was we want to showcase some
Advanced workflow so by that time there
was no application where we were doing
some performance advisory or giving the
recommendation to client in in real time
our existing application was mostly
giving or generating the report maybe
once in a week or once in a month so
there was a delay of at least one week
for producing this report we were
talking about the digital transformation
journey across the companies in our
production Assurance segment as well we
decided to build something quick so the
basic version what we wanted to
demonstrate to any client let's say
there is one asset field where let's say
80 or 100 or less number of oil wells
are available how can we stream the data
the historical data and the streaming
operational data to the cloud and do
some real time surveillance for example
let's say if there is some issue in some
equipment Health some user can be able
to see that equipment Health from any
location instead of directly going to
the oil field to demonstrate this basic
capability and feature of the cloud we
decided to start our journey with one of
the major cloud provider that was Google
Cloud platform and why because Google
Cloud platform was a mandate across all
companies so we we didn't have much
choices that time quickly use the manage
services offered by Google Cloud for
example that time Google was providing
the app engine for creating a manage
services basically developed two pieces
of software one is running on premise to
ingest the data on the cloud and second
piece of software is basically storing
the data on the Google Cloud hosted big
table instance by just creating these
two pieces we were able to build a
simple dashboard to show the equipment
Health do you believe you got it right
the first time or was there any
learnings Midstream that let you to
reevaluate the approach and refine it
first time we didn't it right because I
still
remember the year 2017 when we installed
the first version of the application for
the same client in South Asia where
after installing our on Prem software
that is used to inest the data streaming
from any oil field to the cloud that
piece of software stopped working after
some day later client was contacting us
okay we are not able to see any data on
your surveillance app what could be the
wrong okay so they contacted us but that
time we were new to the cloud world we
not aware about the different aspect of
cloud for example there was no remote
logging facility there was no monitoring
available so we were clueless and the
only option was to ask the client to
share the logs which are available on
the on Prem machine but this learning
helped us to understand okay this is not
the way to work because if there is
certain downtime we need to make some
commitment to the client instead of
client is asking us okay hey your
product is not streaming data we need to
be more proactive in the approach and we
need to change our strategy because we
were mostly coming from the dtop world
so we are mostly relying on the big log
files where we can debug later but no
this is not going to work in the cloud
so as a team we all involved in some
training that time we offered a training
from Google Cloud platform only we
attended different trainings that was
mostly on job training and this training
basically helped us to learn what are
the basic steps involved in building any
cloud ready software and later we
applied this learning for example the
first version was only storing this log
in the on-prem machine but later we
build this capability in the software
itself along with sending the actual
data now this piece of software can send
the log messages as well so it basically
helped us to remotely monitor the on
prame machine and whenever it is down we
can send some message from the cloud and
wake up that machine this basically help
us to learn okay delivering feature is
not only the important part the other
part is operating as well so later we
expand it and put a lot of Matrix in
place and the remote capability of
monitoring all this so in the next
section Maybe let's drill down into the
aspect of which cloud provider did you
end up with and what were your learnings
in that area let's talk first about the
microservices you started with Google
Cloud app app server is that what you
mention yes so we started with Google
app engine that is a managed platform
provided by Google Cloud platform and
did you stay there or was there more
Evolution to the architecture we Del our
first micros service that time we were
only having one micros service which is
mostly responsible for ingesting the
data received from this on premise agent
the first version because we wanted to
deliver something real quick so we built
this service using the managed offering
from Google Cloud that was app engine
but when we started expanding more and
more features to our software platform
that time we want to deploy this
application to as many client as we can
and at the same same time we were
receiving the feedback from different
oil and gas companies who are interested
in our project not all companies was
ready to store their data to Google
Cloud because some companies they have
their own private Cloud somewh using
Azure other companies was using AWS the
discussion was started okay is there any
way to make it Cloud agnostic because we
are still in very initial phase so can
we make our design in that way so
whenever we want to evolve in the future
and we should be able to support a
different Cloud platform that time we
started evaluating cuberes because
kubernetes that time it was in very
initial phase but that time it was only
the and still I think it is mostly
common used platform form to build a
cloud diagnostic micro service so to do
a POC again we migrated this app engine
based service to the cuberes hosted
micro service and we also learned a lot
of things just by migrating this
services from manage platform to the
kuber space and there are lot of
learning involved like how to run a
cuberes cluster and how to scale the
basic units of cuties like part and
deployments we just migrated our first
services and the piece of software and
build and release Pipeline and whatever
scripts we developed in this migration
Journey that formed a base of creating
the new and more and more mro service
and after that for this data Foundation
platform over account we delivered
around 18 to 20 micros service using the
same pattern what we followed for our
first micr service okay got it so you
quickly pivoted from just app engine on
Google Cloud to kubernetes and Cloud
agnostic so hold that thought we come
back to the microservice design
classifications and design but uh in the
meantime can we get into the data layer
can you start with talking about the
types of data and the challenges in any
Upstream production operation there are
different kind of data sets involved for
example what kind of rock properties are
available in particular geographical
location that is called a geological
data other data could be the reservoir
Properties or what kind of simulation
model we are running to get the
production rate there are other things
involve what we call production data
which is mostly flow rates or pressure
temperature fluid composition
and the remaining data type are
basically the streaming data coming in
real time from these facility location
overall we categorize these all
different kind of data into two types
the first one is called the structure
data which is basically static kind of
data and second data is time series data
because most of the data points coming
from any sensors those are time series
in nature and now we want to store this
data on cloud so for time series data we
evaluated the big table so big table is
a scalable cloud storage offering from
Google cloud and for structure data we
used another commercialized database
that is built by a company cognitect
that database name is datomic the most
interesting part in the storage we
wanted to have our work flow all kind of
historical aspect so that we can run
kind of as of date workflow for example
how certain well was looking at certain
date to run these kind of workflows we
need to maintain the history of all data
so we never deleted any data point or
updated anything we are always creating
immutable records of all data it helped
us to track the history and maintain the
auditing of all these data points to
achieve that we use the B temporality
aspect for datomic and big table based
on your explanation I get that Boral
data has two time components associated
with it can you contrast that with time
series data when I'm saying time series
data whenever any sensor is sending us a
data value and time stamp value so we
are mostly interested in in different
characteristic of any oil well for
example we are interested in knowing the
pressure or temperature we also
interested in knowing the oil volume or
gas volume or water volume so when this
data is streamed through in the form of
several data points later we
characterize this time series further to
the sporic and periodic time series for
example let's say some user is running
some workflow which is kind of of well
test kind of workflow that is sporic in
nature sporic means if there is some
event start right now then second event
let's say start maybe after 10 days and
third event could be after 20 days so
that is sporic in nature there is no
fixed time interval between these events
and periodic is like if there is a daily
reading of any particular value for
example there is a daily reading of
pressure or daily reading of the
temperature so this is like a fixed time
interval once we categorize this to
sporic and time series so what is
important for us whenever we are running
any calculation in the form of
recommendation engine so those
calculations should understand the
nature of the time series I mean if it
is or time series because when we
perform the recommendation we also need
to understand if there is a data gap or
something so we need to fill those data
points with some value so that user
understand is it like missing data or
bad data this characterization of the
and time series basically help us
to give the correct recommendation for
structured data why did you specifically
use Atomic as a database yes because our
static data was not time series in
nature so big table was not a obvious
choice to store it so we were looking
for some database which has by default
support of by temporality so datomic is
one of the database which by default its
storage engine supports the temporal
feature so whenever you are storing
anything in atomic it stores as a value
attribute tle format and it always
capture the two aspects of by
temporality the first one is the valid
time valid time means when certain event
was valid in real world for example
let's say I'm doing some drilling
operation so that drilling operation
happened at certain valid time the
second aspect of by temporality is
transaction time transaction time means
when data is actually stored in that
particular database so datomic is one of
the database which has this
characteristic in built so it provides
you the support of running temporal
query what we did we basically to store
the static data let me give you one
example let's say some asset manager who
is looking for the total rollups of all
oil production on certain field so that
asset manager is basically looking for
more than 500 oil wells and checking the
daily production report as of today in
datomic what we are doing we are storing
the hierarchy of this asset for example
if asset manager is in North America and
he's looking into Texas he's looking at
certain city so all these hierarchies
basically stored as versen in versen
format in datomic so whenever someone is
using the API built over datomic any
user can say okay give me the report as
of today or give me the report as of
last year so it will give you the
hierarchy back as of that particular
date that's why datomic was chosen due
to the temp
about big table can we take an example
and explain the data structure and how
that is different from a regular
structured data database yeah sure big
table is basically a database from the
colum family databases so column family
means internally it has a structure of
multi-level map so you can think of it
like a threedimensional map map is like
I'm talking about any hashmap what we
use any programming language and the
second important feature is it is a
column family database so for example
when I'm saying column family it has a
concept of set of column and when I'm
saying a set of column then that calls
column family is the column family
aspect relevant to the time series data
or yes it is relevant for time series
data we use this concept to maintain a
temporality so so for example let's take
example of pressure data let's say there
is one well that well is giving one data
point every hour and we are ingesting
that data point from on prame to Cloud
what will happen whenever let's say I
started my inje 9:00 in morning so there
is a one time stamp 9:00 then another
time is St 10:00 and after that for
whole day I have at least 24 data points
so this is like a physical time stamp
then second time stamp what I'm
assigning when this data point reads to
the cloud Injection Service I'm
assigning another time stamp that what
we call a version time stamp so now we
have these two time stamp so when I'm
storing this data points to Big Table
then I'm using a column family and in
the column family the column column name
is a version Tim stamp and rows are
basically a physical time stamp so
whenever some production engineer is
interested in seeing the pressure value
for as of dat workflow as of dat means
client are always interested in knowing
okay I want to generate report as of
first January or I want to generate
report as of first February so this
wasion time stamp aspect what I'm
storing in the column family that is
basically helping us to maintain the as
of dat workflow aspect and the time stem
the physical time St what I'm storing as
a row key in big table that is basically
helping us to index it and whenever I'm
running any query then I'm considering
these two aspect the column family and
the rowkey both so it will help us to
give us the output for any give me a
pressure data point for T1 to T2 start
dat and end
for as of date so yeah by combining
these two aspect it help us to return
the bite temporary I like to refer
listeners to episode 623 Michael J
fredman on time scale DB this episode
does deal with time series data and the
optimizations for storing in columnar
formats so back to Big Table big table I
understand uh part of Google Cloud but
what happened when you decided to look
at other Cloud vendors also our first
version We Built using big table on
Google cloud and when we migrated for
some client to Azure then in Azure
Cosmos DB was an obvious choice to store
this time series data and we also helped
other client to store and this client
they had their own private cloud or Data
Center and to help these client what we
did we basically use cassendra so
Cassandra has a similar nature and
characteristic for restoring any time
series data and to achieve the
compatibility for the code when we are
moving to one cloud provider to other we
basically use some facade apis so that
we can abstract the nature of quing the
data database so that with minimal
changes and changing the facade layer
only we can easily deploy the same
version of the code to different
databases let's get back to the mid tier
now we've established that you are using
kues to we Cloud agnostic and we've
talked about the databases used
specifically in the area of actually
designing the microservice what was your
approach how did you decide the scope of
a micros service and and the order in
which you would move that to kubernetes
and to the cloud yeah our first piece of
software and delivered microservice was
mostly on the data ingestion part which
was mostly covering if data is ingested
correctly or not but that was only a POC
and we evolved that to first
microservice delivery but later there
are other domain of this problem for
example How can any user ask for
particular okay I'm only interested in
that particular well you ingest data for
this particular well and these many
properties of well for let's say last 50
years so we need some mapping kind of
facility available so that user can map
these property using some Cloud hosted
app the second aspect was okay now we
have one injection domain available and
mapping domain available the third piece
was okay how to to effectively create
apis so that our client can use these
apis and can build their own dashboards
so the third aspect was third scoping
was how to create a tier one Services
over this time series data after that we
want to create some workflow as well
ourself so first part was delivering the
apis only so that client can use it in
their dashboard second was okay what we
can create workflow as our own so the
fourth scope was okay what kind of
services we can build so that we for
example we build some micr service to do
the forecasting of oil well other
microservices for doing the advisory or
recommendation for oil well so these
were mostly the scoping and other
criteria of delivering the microservice
was how effectively we can deliver end
to end feature those are mostly scoped
in a smaller micros service and we also
had a stateful kind of small monolithic
application and those application were
dependent on different smaller micro
services so this monolithic application
delivery cycle was different than the
stateless micro service these are basic
criteria was if you can split it by the
domain or split it by the delivery
frequency did you have to build any
infrastructure components for the pieces
that you deployed to kubernetes for for
the communties service we always relied
on the cloud offered communities
platform we never try to create our own
VM and create our own communties cluster
because lot of complexity involved in it
communties has its own networking
mechanism and there are lots of
complicated pieces involved so we always
uh work with the cloud provider hosted
communities platform for example in
Google Cloud it is G gke in in Azure
communties it's AKs so we always relied
on this managed cuun is offering and for
the infrastructure part we we only
deployed few things like uh if we need
our distributed cache or if we want to
run some database in the communties
cluster that time we only use our own
expertise and we deploy these databases
using the stateful set in cuberes
otherwise we will mostly relying on the
infrastructure coming from the default
cloud provider only okay so you
mentioned a distributor cash was that
used in all your in deployment to all
Cloud providers was it a specific cache
that you used there when we started our
journey with Google Cloud so Google
Cloud had by default cash providing uh
for mamash and redis we developed our
first version with redis
but after operating that red is for few
months what we found the total cost of
operating is little high than expected
and we don't want to invest a lot of
money in the caching storage because our
mostly storage cost was going on big
table because that was our main storage
we decided to run our own redish cluster
over cuberes and to achieve that in the
cuber is there is one option available
to run the stateful set and uh by
default redis provides to run any redis
instance as a high availability mode as
well where we can run a three node redis
cluster to achieve the high availability
so it's a matter of using the state full
set from the cuberes that will help us
to provide some persistent storage and
running a high availability cluster of
Rus on CU pod so main gain was okay now
the cost is reduced but the challenge
was we need to learn about all this
complexity running the stateful set
using persistent storage because it's
not a straightforward thing can you
explain stateful set so cities has this
concept which is called a
stateful set so stateful set is a
feature of cuties whenever we want to
deploy any stateful appliation stateful
application like if you want to run any
message Que incub is the cluster or you
want to run any cache or you want to run
some database kuber is provide a
stateful set resource or we can say
artifact where you can Define your
stateful process when I'm saying
stateful then there is some persistent
storage is also involved so whenever I
want to run some database in cun the
cluster so by default cun's deployment
or ports those are emal in nature I mean
whenever it restart you may lose your
data so that's why those things are not
suitable for your database and with the
stateful set what you can do you can
attach persistent ssds your hard disk so
whenever I installing let's say I want
to run my my datomic database in in
kuber what I will do I will apply the
datomic installation yl file in the form
of State for set and also I will assign
some SSD hard disk so even if my duber
SP or deployment is restarting I will
not lose the state and another important
aspect of it it will assign a unique
identification number to each part so
whenever uh it restart due to some
Network issue or some other issue or we
are applying some patch or upgrade it
automatically assign the same number of
to restart as well so these two concept
like persistent storage in the form of
persistent volume and persistent volume
claim and this unique assignment number
help it to maintain the database State
what about the language that these
microservices were written in can you
cover that when we started writing our
services so we were evaluating different
technology choices that time we
evaluated so in our team we have Java
expertise available so we had so many
software Engineers who have expertise in
Java but with Java framework we we
evaluated spring boot that time it was
available but it was not meeting our
scalability need for example we rote the
first version of Injection Service using
spring it was not meant for running any
streaming kind of injection so we
started looking for other choices so we
evaluated Scala Escala is a functional
programming language so the reason to
chose Scala was not a functional
programming language per se we were
mostly interested in in AKA so AKA is
basically a actor-based framework which
very well-known framework for building
scalable and fall tolerant
applications so we started evaluating
AKA as a frame framework could you
define actor based framework actor based
framework is not a new concept it is
there in the industry since 1970s or
74 I think actor is basically a concept
which is using actor as a logical or
minimal feature whenever you are writing
any code for example in objectoriented
language we use object or create create
any class in actor framework we are
basically creating actors whenever we
are writing some code for example let's
say I'm writing a simple service to
consume data from some database so what
I will do I will create controller layer
for the apis and after that controller
layer I will create another business L
layer so this business layer will be
created using AKA actors so AA provide a
notion or class or interface what you
can whenever you are writing the code
you can extend your classes by using
that actor so internally it will
whenever your code is executing it will
create a small thread and it will assign
a mailbox to that thread so whenever you
are interacting with any aor running
instance you will always interact using
message passing so one actor has no
tight coupling with any other actor so
they can scale independently by just
passing the message from one actor to to
other actor how does this actually
coexist with with kubernetes yeah so AKA
has very good integration with
kubernetes it has its own clustering
mechanism available that called AKA CL
cluster but because we were only using
the cuties platform so we didn't go into
that route that route is specifically
for the people who want to run their own
on Prem data center because we were
using the communities as plat platform
so we started looking the other features
of of AA so our main application was the
injection part okay so injection part
and the other one is is obviously
consumption part so for injection our
main goal is to have the good freshness
of data point for example if let's say
some data point came at SS today at
12:00 so within the 10 seconds I want to
store that data point into our cloud
storage we are looking for some library
or feature where we can achieve the
streaming inje and we can scale it so
AKA provides AKA streaming and one
important point in AA streaming it
basically handle the asynchronous data
injection and other important point is
it is it handle back pressure also so
back pressure is means when uh when we
are running any inje pipeline so there
is a one producer who is producing data
point and another consumer which is
basically consuming this data point and
storing it okay back pressure means
let's say if consumer is still busy and
overwhelmed still processing so it
automatically sends some signal to
producer to stop when we buildt our inje
services or producer was any messaging
maybe Cloud pops up so it is producing
so a streaming is basically taking the
data points in batches and whenever our
big table consumer part is still busy in
writing so it there is no need to do
anything it automatically send signal to
producer okay you hold on I busy right
now so it basically helped us to
maintain the scalability within a
service also so it minimizes the threat
consumption and memory footprint so that
was the main reason to use the streaming
you came up with a canonical data model
you talked about the challenges in
ingesting data and the methodologies now
the data is in how did you use it so now
we have all of the data stored and
everything is stored in datomic and big
tape table now the second aspect of it
using the apis to consume this data and
run a specific production optimization
workflow so when I'm saying production
optimization workflow what our end goal
was to give some recommendation and
action to our end user our end users are
mostly asset managers or production
engineer so that they can make the
corrective action on any incidents
happening on oil field so for example
let's say our data is stored and now I
want to give some recommendation on if
some well is producing more water than
oil so what I will do in my workflow I'm
running some calculation engine this
calculation engine is basically list
listening to the events whenever we are
storing data into a big table and after
that it is running some calculation over
that data and these calculations are
mostly time series in nature and
automatically it is generating some
recommendation okay because your water
flow is increased due to these many
conditions so you can give this
preventive action so in the whenever we
are displaying the results of this
calculation engine to UI so production
engineer looking on the screen they can
see okay the engine is recommending me
this kind of action so it helped us to
make the decision correctly okay now I
can inform someone on the field okay you
can try this so that it will minimize
this kind of incident did you meet your
goal of scaling I think you plan to go
up to 20,000 oil well yeah so we tried
different thing what I covered for the
injection side we tried to achieve the
auto scalability first we tried the
manual scalability then Auto scalability
so with the auto scalability using K and
custom metrics we are able to achieve
the inje scalability aspect and we we
were able to handle one client uh with
8,000 Wells and more than 50 properties
per well streaming 1.2 billion data
points for around 25 years so this is is
for the injection part for consumption
part we wanted to deliver our API
results with minimum latency so there
also we use the cuber default
scalability so it has scalability based
on CPU percentage or memory usage so
we're able to achieve the consumption
scalability by using or monitoring these
metric and within micr service to
achieve the scalability I mean to
minimize the thread and to reduce the
memory footprint of services within AKA
it also provide the monitoring mechanism
for example let's say I have one micros
service and which is basically reading
the data from big table so when I'm
writing this service using AA actors I
can enable the metrix on that AA actors
these metrics are basically where my
actor is involved for example
if some message is waiting on the
mailbox of AA actor I can create a
matrix on on that or some actor is
consuming more CPU than expected so I
can create a metrix on that so by
creating or capturing all this metering
and monitoring I was able to tune the
thread count and different threshold
regarding Min and Max size of this
messages cues within aor so it helped us
to achieve the scalability with within
service so different aspect we covered
different scalability either within the
service or integration point or the
storage you mentioned kada for Autos
scaling can you talk about what is kada
what is the full form so kada stands for
kubernetes event driven
autoscaler so we started using kada
after trying few other solution for
autoscaling I mean we started with
manual scaling where we manually scaled
the number of communities part for
example let's say we deploy our
application to some client and some
sensor is streaming high volume of data
someday but other days it is not
streaming high volume of data so for
that we what we did for we fix the
number of inje pod in cuberes for
example I want to run my inje Pipeline
with a five instances okay but the
problem was with that approach like
maybe some sometimes all parts are
occupied but other times I'm just paying
the money but I'm it's not streaming
anything so second aspect of it we tried
a custom metrix autoscaler which is
available with cuberes so custom metric
means uh by default cumes provide a CPU
based or memory based autoscaling but
custom metrix means you can write any
custom metric so that based on the state
of that metric cuties will Auto scale so
for our case the custom metric was how
number of data points are residing in
the que and waiting for return back to
the time series so we use this a custom
metrix auto scaler but still there was
one problem with this approach it solved
the manual Autos scaling problem now
there is no need to always keep a five
instance of service but it's still uh
for Cuties autoscaler to work it always
need at least one instance of service
running even if that service is not
doing anything but still I need to run
at least one instance of it so we went
one step further we started using a
cuberes event driven autoscaler which is
a cloud Foundation Cloud native open
source project and the Beautiful feature
of kada is it also provide a custom
metric based Auto scaler but there is uh
no need of running even one stance of
your
service so whenever it monitoring it can
scale from the zero state to the desired
number of State let's switch tracks now
and start talking about the migration of
customers from your on premise solution
to the cloud how did that go we had two
kind of customer one existing customer
who are already using our proper It
software and the new customer we what
who wants to onboard Bo with our
production operation platform so one
customer who already using our on-prem
software they were mostly using some
desktop version of application to
migrate these client to Cloud work
workflow the main challenge was
ingesting all this data so for that we
use what I covered already we use the
autonomous agent to ingest this data to
the cloud and after that they started
using the cloud-based workflow the
second client who were new and they had
their data into their data center or
their data provider for that we built a
cloud specific autonomous agent and we
directly ingested their data from their
data center or their data provider to
our cloud and third kind of customer who
were not interested in moving their data
outside their Cloud so we deployed our
services in their data center only so it
helped us to cover different kind of
client like on prame to the cloud or who
are interested in using our cloud
provider or who are not interested in
using so we covered all of them is there
something you would do differently if
you had to do it all over again so I
think when we started and over the years
in last 5 six years we learned a lot so
initially when we started our journey
back in 2016 we were new to the cloud
world I mean how to operate so we
learned a lot I mean earlier when we
started operating a client we didn't use
anything for monitoring or good
monitoring we were not using the SRE
principles service reliability principal
but later over the years we improved a
lot so one good learning what we have
right now and what I particularly use
with my my team so whenever we are
planning some features or new product
for any new client or maybe we are
writing some new feature to the existing
client also so in the planning phase we
are considering the efforts of
operational aspect also I mean we are
not only thinking about okay I need to
write the code and I'm done now we
consider okay how to automate it how to
integrate it properly with CI and CD and
what you need to basically monitor it
and how to push your code without
breaking anything so we consider all
these aspect now what we were not
considering earlier so it Bally helped
us to change our mindset on how to push
code more frequently and without
breaking anything so once we have all
this captured in our Even in our Sprint
planning meeting or any meeting people
start thinking about different things
okay they are always more cautious about
even I'm pushing one line of code but I
need to make sure I'm not breaking
anything would you have any other advice
to other folks that are starting on
their Cloud Journey yeah I I have a few
advice based on my learnings over the
years so what what I understand I mean
cloud is not like a silver bullet to
solve everything most of the people say
okay you will get infinite scalability
and everything but based on my
experience I mean scalability is there
but you need to maintain the maintain
cost also because cost is the aspect
which basically helped any business to
earn Revenue to achieve the infinite
scalability if I'm keep spending or
writing my services or code like that
which is always dependent on cloud and
I'm not focusing on a good quality
software or writing code in good way
then we will end up spending more and
more money and we tried it and we failed
so that's why we learned when I'm
writing anything I need to think about
the cost also because if I'm spending
all money in operating the cloud or
operating or Services I'm not generating
any red Revenue when you onboard a new
customer how much of the existing
infrastructure dual leverage versus
provisioning additional components we
are mostly spending our time if we are
writing some new service for specific
client need for example let's say one
client who is using our software since
last 3 years and for the functionality
we delivered to that client they are
mostly using the non-machine learning
workflow but the same same client
started asking for some other workflow
like okay I want to screen the well
intervention well intervention is a
different concept we didn't use it in
past so we wanted to write some machine
learning workflow so we wrote a
different microservice and we provis
that and for running the machine
learning workflow we use another
enterprise software to achieve that
functionality for that specific client
we only provisioned the machine learning
or mlops thing specific to the client
and other microservice what we build so
it depends on the client need otherwise
most of the thing we are able to achieve
with the existing Services only I see so
sounds like you are still adding
features to round out your solution and
my question was more I think geared
towards potentially when you actually
become SAS if that's your goal in terms
of being when new customers on board do
you actually go ahead and provision
additional components for them
additional infrastructure or are you
more multi-tenant in leveraging things
that are already provision and sharing
infrastructure is there some Vision in
that area yeah I think it's a good point
so for the existing application what we
built for for this data inertion and
consumption part it is mostly single
tenant only single tenant means for one
client the tenci is defined at Cloud
project level but for the new workflow
what we are building right now I just
gave you the example of that machine
learning workflow these workflow are
basically multi- tenant in nature now we
are since last one or two years we
started building multi-tenant
application over this data Foundation
layer we built over the year so this
data Foundation layer is still single
tenant but the workflow we are running
over this data Foundation those are
multi tenant so whenever we are on
boarding a new customer for this
multi-tenant app so the provision is
mostly around provisioning a tenant and
infrastructure associated with it so
yeah new workflows are multi-tenant but
yeah this old data Foundation that is
still s tenant only as we start to wrap
up here abai can you talk about how the
product definition process has changed
as part of your move to the cloud in oil
industry particularly I mean the way we
build product is different than other
companies I mean we are not directly
talking to external clients we have
domain expertise in our own team for
example I have production Engineers or
petroleum
Engineers people in the team so whenever
we are writing a new software the
requirements coming from these domain
people only these domain people we call
product Champions and product analyst so
these people they basically have the
understanding what is going on in the
oil and oil and the guess market so
since last two three years Market is
more towards building SAS and everything
which was not the case until 2020 or so
but yeah now I think they are changing
the focus they want to efficiently
utilize whatever we built and SAS and
multi tenen is one way to achieve it ear
they were not focusing on cost
optimization or other things but now
they understand and they learned over
the years so now they're interested in
offering this technical sales also as a
SAS offering God it sounds like besides
all the technical learnings you also had
business learn from this whole
experience it was great to have you here
a know certainly good luck on your
journey going forward but this was very
extremely useful and helpful insight I
hope our listeners enjoyed it as well
thanks for having me thank thank
you thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by It
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at
SE-R to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack Channel at
seo. slack.com you can also email us at
team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
license
2.5 thanks for listening